Violence Against Women Collection, 1967-1990
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Violence against women collection
1967-1990
MS 410
6 boxes (2.4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection documents efforts to draw attention to and provide resources and support for women victimized by violence. Topics include domestic violence, pornography, rape and sexual assault, shelters, counseling services, and legal support for victims. Materials include creative writing and personal stories, national legislation, reports, newsletters, and a variety of printed material.
The Violence Against Women Collection is comprised of four sections: Domestic violence, Pornography, Rape and sexual assault, and Newsletters. The materials in this collection document the activism of women and organizations that sought to draw attention to and provide resources and support for women victimized by types of violence that, prior to the Women's Liberation movements of the 1970s, were largely ignored in mainstream society. In addition to documenting the legislative and grassroots efforts to create and sustain shelters, counseling services, and legal support for victims of violence, many articles and portions of newsletters articulate a feminist theory that links the patriarchal structure of society to the perpetration of violence against women. The material in this collection dates from the 1970s to the 1990s.
The domestic violence section of this collection consists of articles, creative writing and personal stories, newspaper clippings, national legislation, reports, and a variety of printed material. National efforts, such as the 1980 Domestic Violence Services and Prevention Act, and documents pertaining to local and non-profit initiatives demonstrate the complex relationship between grassroots activism and government intervention in providing adequate services for women and their children seeking to escape domestic violence. While many regions of the United States are represented, the material pertaining to New York state is especially rich. Of particular interest are the documents regarding the workings of the Department of Social Services, the New York legal system, and the local analysis of and response to the federal budget cuts made by the Reagan administration.
The pornography section of this collection is rather brief and contains articles, pamphlets, and printed material professing the view that sexually explicit material objectifies and dehumanizes women, thereby serving to normalize rape and other forms of sexual violence.
The rape and sexual assault portion of this collection contains articles, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and other printed material. While many of the documents reflect the evolution of rape and sexual assault as an issue of concern in the mainstream culture, others illustrate the persistent denial of the problem and the low conviction rate of men accused of rape. Of particular interest are the newspaper clippings, correspondence, and position papers establishing a link between rape and racism.
The newsletters in this collection provide further insight into the ways in which violence against women was taken up as a cause in numerous localities and further documents the political struggles that occurred on the national level.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Multiple donors have contributed to this subject collection.
Search Terms
Family violence--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Pornography--Social aspects--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Rape--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women's shelters--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Crimes against--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Violence against--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Abused women--Services for--United States--History--20th century--Sources
- DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
  - General
    - Articles and papers, 1975-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Bibliographies, 1974, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Booklets, 1977-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Creative writing/personal stories, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1974-82, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National
    - Federal government
      - Department of Justice, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Department of Labor, Women's Bureau, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Legislation
      - Domestic Violence Prevention and Services Act, 1979-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Family Protection Act, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - State overview, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Organizations
      - Business and Professional Women's Foundation, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - National Center on Women and Family Law, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - National Clearinghouse on Domestic Violence: papers, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - National Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1980-81 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Women's Equity Action League, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Regional
    - East
      - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Massachusetts, 1980-82, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - New York
        - Battered husbands and abused children, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - Department of Social Services
          - General, 1979-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
          - Domestic violence program plan, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
          - Domestic violence services, 1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
          - Westchester County, 1979-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - Federal budget cuts: information and local response, 1980-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Governor's Task Force on Domestic Violence:
          - General, 1980-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
          - Report, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - Legal system
          - Criminal court, 1977-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Family court
            - General, 1978-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
            - Report, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Organizations and conferences
          - Proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
          - New York State Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1981-82, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
          - New York State Coalition for Battered Women Planning Conference, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
          - United Way of Central New York, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
          - Volunteers Against Violence Technical Assistance Program, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Reports
          - Existing Services to Battered Women and Their Families, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
          - Research on Service Delivery to Battered Women and Crime Victims, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
          - Battered Women, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
        - Resources
          - Pamphlets, circa 1978-81 (Box 4, Folder 3)
          - Directories, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Midwest
      - General, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Indiana, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Michigan
        - Reports, 1976, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - Training materials, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Nebraska, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - West: General, 1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- PORNOGRAPHY: general, 1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  [See also Periodicals]
- RAPE AND SEXUAL ASSAULT
  - General 1988-1992, undated (Box 5, Folder 7A)
  - Articles, 1967-86, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bibliographies, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Booklets, 1971-1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Creative writing/personal experiences, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1971-81, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - International tribunal on crimes against women, 1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Organizations
    - Feminist Alliance Against Rape (FAAR), undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Rape Crisis Centers, 1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      [See also Women's Liberation Collection]
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Racism, 1974-82, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Valley Women's Vengeance flyer and response 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- NEWSLETTERS
  - Family Violence Bulletin, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kitty Genovese Women's Project, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Majority Report (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The MN Exchange, 1981-83 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - NCASA (National Coalition Against Sexual Assault), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - NCN (National Communications Network for the Elimination of Violence Against Women), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - National Technical Assistance Center on Family Violence Monthly Memo, 1979-81 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Shelter, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Strategies, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - WAVAW (Women Against Violence Against Women), undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Moore, Donna M., ed. Battered Women (Beverly hills: Sage Publications,1979)